Hello, and welcome to Lesson 27 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好，这里是 Wolfram U的微积分入门，第27课
The topic of this lesson is the substitution rule.
本次课程的主题是 换元法
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
让我们从本课的简要概述开始
In the last lesson, we talked about
上节课我们说到了
some rules for calculating integrals,
一些计算积分的规则
and we learned a few simple rules.
我们学了几个简单的
For example, we can now do the integral of x^2 and get back x^3/3,
比如我们现在可以计算 x^2 的积分得到 x^3/3
so that’s x^a giving you x^(a + 1)/(a + 1), the power rule.
所以 x^a 的积分是 x^(a + 1)/(a + 1)，这是幂规则
The rules we learned cannot help us in more difficult cases.
这个规则对于更难的情况无能为力
For example, if I gave you the function 10Sin[3x],
例如 给你的函数是 10Sin[3x]
then those rules would not work, and they will not work
那些规则就不能用了，将来也做不了
for this harder problem involving a square root radical.
包含平方根根式的这个难题
Here are the functions and their plots.
这里有函数和他的图像
What you notice is that these are quite interesting functions,
注意到这些是非常有趣的一些函数
so surely you would like to integrate them.
因此 你当然希望能把他们积出来
The question is how do we do that,
问题是我该怎么算
and that is the goal of this lesson.
这就是这节课的目标
The goal of this lesson is to try and calculate such integrals
这节课我们要计算那些积分
using what is called the substitution rule.
使用 换元法
But to do that, I must recall the chain rule for you.
但是事先，必须复习一下链式法则
The chain rule says that if you have two functions, f and g
链式法则是说如果有两个函数 f 和 g
—so you have f[x] and g[x]—then the derivative of the composition
——所以你现在有 f[x] 和 g[x]——然后他们的 复合函数 的导数
f[g[x]] is f'[g[x]] * g'[x].
f[g[x]] 的导数是 f'[g[x]] * g'[x]
Here’s the rule a little more formally using D,
这是形式使用D的规则，
and you get back the answer that you expected.
并且你可以得到希望的答案
Now of course, every time you have
在今天的课上 每当你用了
a rule for derivatives like this one,
类似刚才那个求导法则
then you have a rule for integration, so now that says that
那你有有了一个积分法 换句话说
the integral of f'[g[x]] * g'[x] is f[g[x]],
积分 f'[g[x]] * g'[x] 得 f[g[x]]
and that is the basis for the substitution rule.
就是 换元法 的基础
Let’s go a little deeper and talk about the substitution rule.
我们稍微深入讨论一下 换元法
Let’s say you want to evaluate this integral over here.
假设要算这个积分
What we’ll do is to simplify things, we’ll set u to be g[x].
简单的 设 g[x] 为 u
Now you get f'[u], and you’ll get this g'[x]dx.
现在有 f'[u] 并且有 g'[x]dx
But then if you think about it, the derivative of u is g'[x],
但是考虑到 u 的导数是 g'[x]
so that says that roughly speaking, du = g'[x]dx.
不加证明的有 du = g'[x]dx
That’s a differential statement, but it’s correct.
这是（导数的）另外一种说法而已，没错
Basically what we’ve done is
基本上 我们要做的就是
to reduce this rather difficult-looking integral on the left
简化左边这个看起来更麻烦的积分
to a rather simple-looking integral on the right,
得到右边这个看起来简单点的积分
and that is the substitution rule for integrals.
这就是 积分换元法
For example, if I said find the integral of 3Sin[3x]dx,
比如 积分 3Sin[3x]dx
then you set u to be 3x.
设 3x 为 u
So du is 3dx because that’s the derivative of 3x.
因此 du 就是 3dx ，是 3x 的导数
That 3 over here and the dx over there combine, and you get Sin[u]du.
这边的 3 和 dx 一结合 就得到 Sin[u]du
Then we can’t stop over here because u is 3x,
然后还没结束，因为 u 是 3x
so the answer is –Cos[3x].
答案是  –Cos[3x]
You can check that directly with Integrate,
你可以直接用 Integrate 来验算
and you do get back the right answer.
得到的是同样的答案
That’s the rule for substitution,
这就叫 换元法
namely, you set u to be g[x] and then proceed from there.
将 g[x] 设为 u 然后继续
As an example, let’s take another trig function, 10Sin[3x].
例如 对另一个三角函数 10Sin[3x]
Again, you set u to be 3x, so du is 3dx.
再一次，我们设 3x 为 u 因此 du 就是 3dx
But then you have a 10 over here, so you make a small adjustment
但是你这里是 10（不是 3 ）就需要做点调整
and write it as (10/3) * 3, and so you get back that
改写为 (10/3) * 3 这就回到刚才了
the integral really is (10/3)Sin[u].
积分是 (10/3)Sin[u]
You integrate that, but then recall that u is 3x,
积出来后 回想 u 是 3x
so you plug that back in and you get back the exact answer,
再重新代回去就得到最后答案
which is what Integrate would give you if you tried it directly.
和你直接用 Integrate 算的一样
Okay. Let’s go a step further now
好 我们更进一步
and talk about an algebraic function.
讨论代数函数
That’s the second function from the introduction.
这是介绍中的第二个函数
Here you think of this inside the square root sign as being u,
这里将根式里的东西设为 u
so u is x^3 + 3.
于是 u 就是 x^3 + 3
So du = 3x^2dx because that’s the derivative of 3x^3 + 3,
所以  du = 3x^2dx 因为它是 3x^3 + 3 的导数
but then you think to yourself you’ve got a 2 over here,
但是你自己看这里有个 2
so we need a small adjustment.
所以 微调一下
We’ll add to this 2/3 * 3, so you have that
改写为 2/3 * 3，就有
the integral is 2/3√u with respect to u.
这个积分是 2/3√u 里面带着 u
You plug in the expression for u
把 u 的式子代回去
and you get back the answer in terms of x,
得到的就是以 x 为变量的答案
and of course Integrate gives just the same answer in this case.
当然 Integrate 这时候给出了相同的答案
Let’s now go on to a slightly harder example
我们看一个稍有难度的例子
where you have a kind of rational algebraic function.
是这种根式型函数
Here you set u to be 5 – 5x^2,
设 5 – 5x^2 是 u
so du is –10xdx because that’s the derivative of u.
所以 du 是 –10xdx，是 u 的导数
Then you tell yourself that you have a 2x over here,
然后你告诉自己这里有个 2x
so we need a small adjustment, so that is (–2/10) *  –10,
因此做点调整，改写成 (–2/10) *  –10
and you get back the integral of u over here.
你就得到了 u 的积分
You plug in the expression for u as 5 – 5x^2,
将 u 就是 5 – 5x^2 代回去
and of course integrate will give you back
当然 Integrate 也能给你积出来
just the same answer in this case.
答案一样
Okay. Slightly harder example: you have f[x] = x^3√(3 – x^2).
好，再难一点：考虑 f[x] = x^3√(3 – x^2)
You set u to be 3 – x^2.
设 3 – x^2 为 u
That’s what’s inside the square root sign.
这就是根式里的东西
So du is –2xdx.
所以 du 就是 –2xdx
Now another problem: you need to integrate the x^3 carefully
现在的另一个问题是：要小心的去积分 x^3
as the –2x bit from here and the part that’s left over,
从这里的 –2x 到剩下的部分
which is x^2, but x^2 is just 3 – u,
是 x^2，但是 x^2 就是 3 – u
and that’s how I get the part over here.
这就是我如何得到了这一项
The integral becomes (–1/2)(3 – u)√u.
积分变为 (–1/2)(3 – u)√u
You integrate that.
你把它积出来了
You plug in the expression, and of course Integrate will give you
你代回去，当然 Integrate 也能给你
just the same answer in this case as well.
算出相同的答案
Well, there’s a slight difference because you have
哦，这里有一点不一样 因为
a negative sign inside over here and outside,
内外都有一个负号
but essentially they are the same answer.
但是事实上是一个答案
Now the point is that you have two answers,
现在的重点是 两个答案
one in terms of u and the other in terms of x.
一个被 u 表示 一个被 x 表示
As far as this example goes, it’s the x answer that matters,
就本例而言，最重要的是由  x  表示的答案
but when you go on to definite integrals,
但是当你继续做定积分的时候
then you want to actually plug in limits, and at that point,
你实际上想确定上下限 在那一点
we have two ways of going about it.
我们有两种方式去得到它
First of all, what you could do is
第一种 你可以这样做
you could work with the expression involving x, the x answer,
你可以用含  x 的表达式 带 x 的答案
and plug in the upper and lower limits.
然后加上限和下限
Let’s say you want to go from 0 to 1.
比如我们想从 0 到 1
You plug in the value of the x answer at 1 and then at 0,
你就要把 x 的值代为 1 和 0
and you get back the answer over here.
然后就能得到答案
But you could also keep the u form, and if you do that,
但是你也可以保留  u，如果你这么做
you’ve got to be careful because when x goes from 0 to 1,
你就要小心一点，当  x 取 0 和 1 的时候
then u goes from 3 to 2.
u 取的是 3 和 2
That’s because u is defined in terms of x.
这是因为 u  是由 x 的式子定义的
Here’s the answer again from the u method,
用 u 方法得到的还是这个答案
and you get back just the same result.
你得到相同的结果
You can check it all with Integrate, and you have
你可以用 Integrate 验算 你有
the first answer is the u answer going from 3 to 2.
第一个答案是 u 从 3 到 2
The other one is from 0 to 1 for x,
另一个是  x 从 0 到 1
and you get back the same result in both the cases.
两种算法答案相同
The point is that when you have a definite integral,
重点是当你做定积分时
then you could either work in the u picture or the x picture,
你可以用 u 的图 或者是 x 的图
and they are both convenient in some ways.
他们在某些时候都很方便
The u answer tends to be simpler,
u 答案往往更简单
but you need to change the limits.
但是你要小心上下限的变化
The x answer tends to be more complicated,
x 答案更复杂
but then you have the limits given to you.
但是上下限是直接给出的
You should decide which one is better in each case.
应该每次都选较好的方式去做
That brings me to the end of this lesson.
课就到这里了
The main point is the substitution rule lets you
重点是 换元法 让你
calculate integrals using the chain rule in reverse.
计算积分的时候逆用链式法则
This rule is essentially a reverse chain rule.
换元法的实质就是逆用链式法则
What you do is you always begin by making a substitution u,
始终从做换元  u  开始
a suitable one.
一个合适的换元
Then you find du and modify the integral as required.
然后计算  du  并根据需要改写积分
Then you plug back the expression for u after integrating
积分完代入 u 的表达式
and you get back the result.
就能得到结果
But of course when working with definite integrals,
但是 在做定积分时
you could either work with the original endpoints and x,
即可以用原上下限和  x ，
or change the endpoints and work with u.
也能改变形式用 u
That’s the essence of this rule.
这是这条规则的本质
In the next lesson, we’ll apply these ideas
下节课 我们会用这个方法
to compute the area between two curves.
计算两条曲线之间的面积
But before doing that, do review the lesson.
但是在此之前 好好复习
It’s quite a difficult lesson because you’ll need this rule
这是非常困难的一课 因为你需要用这个方法
again and again, and you must have some practice with applying it.
算一遍又一遍 你必须做一些练习来用它
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.
本节课到此为止，再见
翻译：兰州大学 周怀尚